<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="2"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="exp" docName="draft-ietf-nmop-network-anomaly-lifecycle-05" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="network-anomaly-lifecycle">An Experiment: Network Anomaly
    Detection Lifecycle</title>

    <author fullname="Vincenzo Riccobene" initials="V." surname="Riccobene">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city>Dublin</city>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country>Ireland</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>vincenzo.riccobene@huawei-partners.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Thomas Graf" initials="T" surname="Graf">
      <organization>Swisscom</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Binzring 17</street>

          <city>Zurich</city>

          <code>8045</code>

          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </postal>

        <email>thomas.graf@swisscom.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Wanting Du" initials="W" surname="Du">
      <organization>Swisscom</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Binzring 17</street>

          <city>Zurich</city>

          <code>8045</code>

          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </postal>

        <email>wanting.du@swisscom.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Alex Huang Feng" initials="A." surname="Huang Feng">
      <organization>INSA-Lyon</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city>Lyon</city>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>alex.huang-feng@insa-lyon.fr</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="08" month="December" year="2025"/>

    <area>Operations and Management</area>

    <workgroup>NMOP</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>Network Anomaly Detection is the act of detecting problems in
      the network. Accurately detecting problems is very challenging for
      network operators in production networks. Good results require a
      lot of expertise and knowledge around both the implied network
      technologies and the connectivity services provided to customers,
      apart from a proper monitoring infrastructure. In order to
      facilitate network anomaly detection, novel techniques are being
      introduced, including programmatical, rule-based and AI-based,
      with the promise of improving scalability and the hope to keep a
      high detection accuracy. To guarantee acceptable results, the
      process needs to be properly designed, adopting well-defined
      stages to accurately collect evidence of anomalies, validate their
      relevancy and improve the detection systems over time,
      iteratively.</t>

      <t>This document describes a well-defined approach on managing the
      lifecycle process of a network anomaly detection system, spanning
      across the recording of its output and its iterative refinement,
      in order to facilitate network engineers to interact with the
      network anomaly detection system, enable the "human-in-the-loop" 
      paradigm and refine the detection abilities over time. The major
      contributions of this document are: the definition of three key
      stages of the lifecycle process, the definition of a state machine
      for each anomaly annotation on the system and the definition of
      YANG data models describing a comprehensive format for the anomaly
      labels, allowing a well-structured exchange of those between all
      the interested actors.</t>
    </abstract>


    <note removeInRFC="true">
      <name>Discussion Venues</name>

      <t>This note is to be removed before publishing as an RFC.</t>

      <t>Discussion of this document takes place on the Operations and
      Management Area Working Group Working Group mailing list
      (nmop@ietf.org), which is archived at <eref
      target="https://mailarchive.ietf.org/arch/browse/nmop/"/>.</t>

      <t>Source for this document and an issue tracker can be found at
      <eref target="https://github.com/network-analytics/draft-ietf-nmop-network-
      anomaly-lifecycle/"/>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>
      The main objective of a network anomaly detection syste is to
      identify Relevant States of the network as those are States that
      could lead to problems or might be clear indications of problems 
      already happening.
      </t>

      <t>An architecture for network anomaly detection is defined in 
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-nmop-network-anomaly-architecture"/>.</t>


      <t>It is still remarkably difficult to gain a full understanding
      and a complete perspective of "if" and "how" a Relevant State is
      actually an indication of a Problem or it is just unexpected, but
      has no impact on services and end users. Providers of solutions
      for network anomaly detection should aim at increasing accuracy,
      by minimizing False Positives and False Negatives. Moreover, the
      behaviour of the network naturally changes over time. When more
      connectivity services are deployed, more customers are on-boarded
      to the network, network devices are upgraded or replaced, and
      therefore, it is almost  impossible to identify anomaly detection
      techniques that can keep working accurately over time, without
      changing the detection criterias (or methodologies) over time.</t>

      <t>This opens up to the necessity of further validating notified
      Relevant States to check if a detected symptom is actually
      impacting connectivity services: this might require different
      actors (both human and algorithmic) to act together during the
      process and refine their understanding across the network anomaly
      lifecycle.</t>

      <t>Finally, once validation has happened, this might lead to
      refinements to the logic that is used by the detection, so that
      this process can improve the detection accuracy over time.</t>

      <t>Performing network anomaly detection is a process that requires
      a continuous learning and continuous improvement. Relevant States
      are detected by aggregating and understanding Symptoms, then
      validated, confirming that Symptoms actually impacted connectivity
      services and eventually need to be further analyzed by performing 
      postmortem analysis to identify any potential adjustment to
      improve the detection capability. Each of these steps represents
      an opportunity to learn and refine the process, and since
      implementations of these steps might also be provided by different
      parties and/or products, this document also contributes a formal
      data model to capture and exchange Symptom  information across the
      lifecycle.</t>

      <t>The adjustment of the detection process can happen after
      problems  are solved and well understood, so the learning can be
      transferred into the detection system for future faster
      detections. For this reason, the network anomaly Detection
      lifecycle mainly relates to the Postmortem stage of the network
      anomaly detection process, as described in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-nmop-network-anomaly-architecture"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="status" title="Status of this document">
      <t>This document is experimental. The main goal of this document
      is to propose an iterative lifecycle process to network anomaly
      detection by proposing a data model for network anomaly metadata
      to be addressed at different lifecycle stages.</t>

      <t>The experiment consists of verifying whether the approach is
      usable in real use case scenarios to support proper refinement and
      adjustments of network anomaly detection algorithms. The
      experiment can be deemed successful if validated at least with an
      open-source implementation successfully applied with real
      networks.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="notation" title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
      "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",
      "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to
      be interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
      <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all
      capitals, as shown here.</t>

      <t>This document makes use of the terms defined in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-nmop-terminology"/>.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>State</t>

          <t>Problem</t>

          <t>Alarm</t>

          <t>Symptom</t>
          
          <t>Relevance and Relevant State</t>

          <t>Network Anomaly</t>

        </list></t>

      <t>The following terms are used as defined in <xref
      target="RFC9417"/>.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Metric</t>

          <t>Intent</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>The following terms are defined in this document.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Annotator: Is a human or an algorithm which produces
          metadata by describing anomalies with Symptoms.</t>

          <t>False Positive: Is a detected anomaly which has been
          identified during the postmortem to be not anomalous.</t>

          <t>False Negative: Is anomalous but has not been identified by
          the anomaly detection system.</t>

          <t>Confidence Score: Indicates how confident the detector
					detected an outlier. The value ranges between 0 and 100. The
					higher the value the higher the confidence. For example, if
					the normal value of the operational-data is in the range of
					0-10 and the detected value is 1000, a confidence score of 100
					could make sense. Where a detected value of 100 would lead to
					a confidence level of 10. The Confidence Score is applicable
					to a single anomaly or for a detection strategy on one ore
					more anomalies.</t>

          <t>Concern Score: Indicates how concerned network operation on
					connectivity service degradation should be. The value ranges
					between 0 and 100. The higher the value the higher the
					concern. The concern takes the confidence and the knowledge,
					<xref section="3.5.1" sectionFormat="of"
          target="I-D.ietf-nmop-network-anomaly-architecture"/>, of the
					detection system into account. For example, if the normal
					value of the operational-data is in the range of 0-10, the
					detected value is 20, from data profiling, section 3.5.1.3 of
					architecture, it learned that given time series has usually
					not many deviations from normal and therefore is rather
					sensitive to deviations, a Concern Score of 40 could make
					sense. The Confidence Score is applicable to one ore more
					anomalies. In case of multiple anomalies, knowledge from
					expert rules as in <xref section="3.5.1.1" sectionFormat="of"
          target="I-D.ietf-nmop-network-anomaly-architecture"/> or
					network modelling as in section <xref section="3.5.1.2"
					sectionFormat="of"
          target="I-D.ietf-nmop-network-anomaly-architecture"/> are
					taken into account in the calculation of the Confidence Score.
					</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Defining_desired_states" title="Defining Desired States">
      <t>The Problem, as defined in <xref target="introduction"/>,
      provide the scope for what to be looking for when detecting
      network anomalies. This poses the attention on a significant
			Problem that network operators have to face: the definition of
			what is to be considered "desirable" or "undesirable". It is not
			always easy to detect if a network is operating in an undesired
			State at a given point in time. To approach this, network
			operators can rely on different methodologies, more or less
			deterministic and more or less sensitive: on the one side, the
			definition of Intents (including Service Level Objectives and
			Service Level Agreements) which approaches the Problem top-down;
			on the other side, the definition of Symptoms, by mean of
			solutions like <xref target="RFC9417">SAIN</xref>, <xref
			target="RFC9418"/> and <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-nmop-network-anomaly-architecture"/>, which
      approaches the Problem bottom-up. At the center of these
      approaches, there are the so-called Symptoms, explaining what is
      not working as expected in the network, sometimes also providing
      hints towards issues and their causes.</t>

      <t>One of the more deterministic approaches is to rely on Symptoms
      based on measurable service-based KPIs, for example, by using
      Service Level Indicators, Objectives and Agreements <xref
      target="RFC9543"/>. This is the case when rules on SLOs and SLIs
      are manually defined once and the used afterwards for detection at
      runtime.</t>

      <t>However, defining SLOs in a "static way" can bring some 
      challenges as well, related to the dynamic nature of networks 
      and services.</t>

      <t>Alternative methodologies rely on a more "relaxed" approach 
      to detect symptoms and their impact to services as a way to 
      generate analytical data out of operational data. 
      For instance:</t>

      <dl>
        <dt>SAIN</dt>

        <dd>introduces the definition and exposure of Symptoms as a
        mechanism for detecting those concerning behaviors in a more
        deterministic way. Moreover, the concept of "impact score" has
        been introduced by SAIN, to indicate what is the expected degree
        of impact that a given Symptom will have on the services relying
        on the related subservice to which the Symptom is attached.</dd>
      </dl>

      <dl>
        <dt>Cosmos Bright Lights</dt>

        <dd>introduces the concept of "Concern Score" to indicate what
        is the degree of concern that a given Symptom could cause a
        degradation for a connectivity service.</dd>
      </dl>

      <t>In general, defining boundaries between desirable vs.
      undesirable in an accurate fashion requires continuous iterations
      and improvements coming from all the stages of the network anomaly
      detection lifecycle, by which network engineers can transfer what
      they learn through the process into new Symptom definitions and,
      ultimately, into refinements of the detection algorithms.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="lifecycle_network_anomaly"
             title="Lifecycle of a Network Anomaly">
      <t>The lifecycle of a network anomaly can be articulated in three
      stages, structured as a loop: Detection, Validation, Refinement.</t>

      <figure anchor="simplified_lifecycle"
              title="Anomaly Detection Refinement Lifecycle">
        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
                       +-------------+
            +--------> |  Detection  | ---------+
Adjustments |          +-------------+          | Symptoms
            |                                   |
            |                                   v
    +------------+                       +------------+
    | Refinement |<--------------------- | Validation |
    +------------+        Problem        +------------+
                        Confirmation
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>Each of these stages can either be performed by a network
      expert or an algorithm or complementing each other.</t>

      <t>The network anomaly metadata is generated by an Annotator,
      which can be either a human expert or an algorithm. The Annotator can
      produce the metadata for a network anomaly, for each stage of the
      cycle and even multiple versions for the same stage. In each
      version of the network anomaly metadata, the Annotator indicates
      the list of Symptoms that are part of the network anomaly taken
      into account. The iterative process is about the identification of
      the right set of Symptoms.</t>

      <section anchor="network_anomaly_detection"
               title="Network Anomaly Detection">
        <t>The Network Anomaly Detection stage is about the continuous
        monitoring of the network through Network Telemetry <xref
        target="RFC9232"/> and the identification of Symptoms. One of
        the main requirements that operators have on network anomaly
        detection systems is the high accuracy. This means having a
        small number of False Negatives, i.e. Symptoms causing
        connectivity service impact are not missed, and low amount of
        False Positives, i.e. Symptoms that are actually innocuous are
        not picked up.</t>

        <t>As the detection stage is becoming more and more automated
        for production networks, the identified Symptoms might point
        towards three potential kinds of behaviors:</t>

        <t>i. those that are surely corresponding to an impact on
        connectivity services, (e.g. the breach of an SLO),</t>

        <t>ii. those that will cause Problems in the future (e.g. rising
        trends on a timeseries Metric hitting towards saturation),</t>

        <t>iii. those or which the impact to connectivity services
        cannot be confirmed (e.g. sudden increase/decrease of timeseries
        Metrics, anomalous amounts of log entries, etc.).</t>

        <t>The first category requires immediate intervention (a.k.a.
        the problem is "confirmed"), the second one provides pointers
        towards early signs of an problem potentially happening in the
        near future (a.k.a. the problem is "forecasted"), and the third
        one requires some analysis to confirm if the detected Symptom
        requires any attention or immediate intervention (a.k.a. the
        problem is "potential"). As part of the iterative improvement
        required in this stage, one that is very relevant is the gradual
        conversion of the third category into one of the first two,
        which would make the network anomaly detection system more
        deterministic. The main objective is to reduce uncertainty
        around the raised alarms by refining the detection algorithms.
        This can be achieved by either generating new Symptom
        definitions, adjusting the weights of automated algorithms or
        other similar approaches.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="network_anomaly_validation"
               title="Network Anomaly Validation">
        <t>The key objective for the validation stage is clearly to
        decide if the detected Symptoms are signaling a real problem
        (a.k.a. requires action) or if they are to be treated as false
        positives (a.k.a. suppressing the alarm). For those Symptoms
        surely having impact on connectivity services, 100% confidence
        on the fact that a network problem is happening can be assumed.
        For the other two categories, "forecasted" and "potential",
        further analysis and validation is required.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="network_anomaly_refinement"
               title="Network Anomaly Refinement">
        <t>After validation of a problem, the service provider performs
        troubleshooting and resolution of the problem. Although the
        network might be back in a desired State at this point, network
        operators can perform detailed postmortem analysis of Problems
        with the objective to identify useful adjustments to the
        prevention and detection mechanisms (for instance improving or
        extending the definition of SLIs and SLOs, refining
        concern/impact scores, etc.), and improving the accuracy of the
        validation stage (e.g. automating parts of the validation,
        implementing automated root cause analysis and automation for
        remediation actions). In this stage of the lifecycle it is
        assumed that the problem is under analysis.</t>

        <t>After the adjustments are performed to the network anomaly
        detection methods, the cycle starts again, by "replaying" the
        network anomaly and checking if there is any measurable
        improvement in the ability to detect Problems by using the
        updated method. In some cases, detection can be improved by
				capturing additional or more appropriate metrics.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="label_store" 
      title="Introducing a Label Store for Network Anomaly labels">
      <t>
      The information that is produced at each stage needs to be 
      persisted and retrieved to perform the network anomaly 
      lifecycle.</t>

      <t>The lifecycle begins with the detector notifying anomalies 
      to the "Alarm and Problem Management System" and to the
      "Postmortem System" according to (see <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-nmop-network-anomaly-architecture"/>). In this
      case the Postmortem system is identified as the Label Store. Once
      the notification arrives to the Label Store, the anomaly label is
      persisted. In the following stages (i.e. validation and
      refinement), the information about the labels are retrieved,
      reviewed, modified and persisted again, generating every time a
      new version of the same annotation, or tagging the annotation as
      irrelevant, if it would be necessary to remove it.</t>

      <t>
      In the following sections, the following are defined:
      </t>

      <list style="symbols">
        <t>a state machine for a label</t>
        <t>a YANG data model for the notification sent by the Detector 
        to the Label Store</t>
        <t>a YANG data model to the define the interrogation (and
        retrieval) of the persisted labels from the label store.</t>
      </list> 
    </section>

    <section anchor="network_anomaly_state_machine"
             title="Network Anomaly State Machine">
      <t>In the context of this document, from a network anomaly
      detection point of view a Problem is defined as a collection of
      interrelated Symptoms, as specified in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-nmop-network-anomaly-semantics"/>.
      </t>

      <t>The understanding of a Problem can change over time. Moreover,
      multiple actors are involved in the process of refining this
      understanding in the different stages.</t>

      <t>From this perspective, a problem can be refined according to
      the following Stages (<xref target="state_machine"/>).
      </t>

      <figure anchor="state_machine" title="Network Anomaly State Machine">
        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
        +-------+                       +---------+
        | Final |                       | Initial |----------------+
        +---^---+                       +---------+                |
            |                                |                     |
            |                          +-----+---------+           |
+-----------------------+     +--------|---------------|------+    |
|  +-----------------+  |     | +------v-----+  +------v----+ |    |
|  |    Detection    |------->| |  Problem   |  |  Problem  | |    |
|  |     Adjusted    |  |     | | Forecasted |  | Potential | |    |
|  +--------^--------+  |     | +------------+  +-----------+ |    |
|           |           |     +--------|--Detection---|-------+    |
|           |           |              |              |            |
|           |           |              +------- ----- +            |
|           |           |                      |                   |
|           |           |                      |                   |
|           |           |                      |                   |
|           |           |                      v                   |
| +---------|--------+  |     +-----------Validation------------+  |
| |     Problem      |  |     |  +-----------+                  |  |
| |     Analyzed     |<-------|  |  Problem  |   |  Problem  |  |  |
| +------------------+  |     |  | Discarded |   | Confirmed |<-|--+
|                       |     |  +-----|-----+   +-----------+  |
+-------Refinement------+     +---------------------------------+
                                       |
                                   +---v---+
                                   | Final |
                                   +-------+
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>The knowledge gained at each stage is encoded as a list of
      anomaly labels that can be stored on a Label Store.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="network_anomaly_data model" 
        title="Network Anomaly Lifecycle Data Model">

      <t>The data model provides support for "human-in-the-loop", 
      allowing for network experts to validate and adjust network
      anomaly labels and detection systems. An example of
      human-in-the-loop has been demonstrated with Antagonist <xref
      target="Antagonist"/>, by building a User Interface that interacts 
      with an API based on this data model.</t>

      <t>The base for the modules is the "ietf-relevant-state" data
      model. Relevant State is at the root of the data model, with its
      parameters (ID, description, start-time, end-time) and a
      collection of anomalies. This allows the Relevant State to be
      considered as a container of anomalies.</t>
      
      <t>Each anomaly is characterized by some intrinsic fields (such as 
      id, version, stage, description, start-time, end-time, confidence
      score and pattern) Particularly the confidence score is a measure
      of how confident was the detector in considering the given anomaly
      as an anomalous behaviour.</t>

      <t>Data patterns are being classified into different types.
      currently the model accommodates, drop, spike mean-shift,
			seasonality-shift and trend as types of data patterns and can
			be easily extended by adding new YANG identities.</t>
      
      <t>Each anomaly also includes the operational-data, symptom and
			the service container. These containers are placeholders to
			represent the information whoch operational data was used, the
			symptom (what exactly is happening as anomalous behaviour) was
			observed and the connectivity service (what entity is affected by
			the anomaly). In particular, for what concerns the symptom, a
			confidence and concern score is defined as necessary field, which
			has the meaning of expressing how cofident the anomaly was
			detected and much potentially it is impacting the connectivity
			service.</t>

      <t>In case additional information related to the symptom and to 
      the connectivity service need to be provided, augmentation would
			be the appropriate mechanism to do so. An example of this is
      provided in <xref 
      target="I-D.ietf-nmop-network-anomaly-semantics"/>, where an
      augmentation of both symptom and service is provided for the
      specific case of anomaly labels related to connectivity services.
      </t>
        
      <t>Also a list of various actors that are involved in the
      process is presented as following:
        <dl>
          <dt>In the detection stage:</dt>
            <dd>
              the detectors are either Network Engineers 
              and/or Automatic detectors 
              (including Rule-based detectors and ML-based detectors)
            </dd>
        </dl>

        <dl>
          <dt>In the validation stage:</dt>
          <dd>
            the validators are Network Engineers manually validating
            the labels
          </dd>
        </dl>

        <dl>
          <dt>In the refinement stage:</dt>
          <dd>
            the refiners are either Data Scientists and/or Automatic 
            Refiners (including systems that automatically refine 
            the detection systems, based on the validated labels).
          </dd>
        </dl>
      </t>

      <t>The data model defines a Relevant State container and a Relevant
      State notification: the notification is primarily used by the
      Network Anomaly Detector, to notify the "Alarm and Problem
      Management System"  and the "Postmortem System" (see <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-nmop-network-anomaly-architecture"/>); the
      container instead is used inside the Postmortem system to exhance
      anomaly detection lables between the anomaly detection stages
      defined above (validation, refinement, detection).</t>
      
      <section anchor="network-anomaly-model-tree" 
          title="Overview of the Data Model for the Relevant State and
          all the related entities">
        <t>The "ietf-relevant-state" module defines a Relevant State
        container to report associated anomalies and a
        "relevant-state-notification" used for exchanging the relevant
        State information. The following YANG tree diagram <xref
        target="RFC8340"/> shows the "ietf-relevant-state" model.</t>
        <sourcecode type="yangtree"><![CDATA[
module: ietf-relevant-state
  +--rw relevant-state
     +--rw id                  yang:uuid
     +--rw uri?                inet:uri
     +--rw description?        string
     +--rw start-time          yang:date-and-time
     +--rw end-time?           yang:date-and-time
     +--rw strategy?           string
     +--rw confidence-score?   score
     +--rw concern-score       score
     +--rw stage               identityref
     +--rw (service)?
     +--rw anomaly* [id revision]
        +--rw id                  yang:uuid
        +--rw revision            yang:counter32
        +--rw uri?                inet:uri
        +--rw stage               identityref
        +--rw description?        string
        +--rw start-time          yang:date-and-time
        +--rw end-time?           yang:date-and-time
        +--rw confidence-score?   score
        +--rw pattern?            identityref
        +--rw annotator
        |  +--rw id?               yang:uuid
        |  +--rw name              string
        |  +--rw version?          string
        |  +--rw annotator-type?   enumeration
        +--rw operational-data
        |  +--rw topic-name?     inet:host-name
        |  +--rw subject-name?   inet:host-name
        +--rw symptom!
           +--rw id               yang:uuid
           +--rw concern-score    score

  notifications:
    +---n relevant-state-notification
       +--ro publisher
       |  +--ro id?        yang:uuid
       |  +--ro name       string
       |  +--ro version?   string
       +--ro id                  yang:uuid
       +--ro uri?                inet:uri
       +--ro description?        string
       +--ro start-time          yang:date-and-time
       +--ro end-time?           yang:date-and-time
       +--ro strategy?           string
       +--ro confidence-score?   score
       +--ro concern-score       score
       +--ro stage               identityref
       +--ro (service)?
       +--ro anomaly* [id revision]
          +--ro id                  yang:uuid
          +--ro revision            yang:counter32
          +--ro uri?                inet:uri
          +--ro stage               identityref
          +--ro description?        string
          +--ro start-time          yang:date-and-time
          +--ro end-time?           yang:date-and-time
          +--ro confidence-score?   score
          +--ro pattern?            identityref
          +--ro annotator
          |  +--ro id?               yang:uuid
          |  +--ro name              string
          |  +--ro version?          string
          |  +--ro annotator-type?   enumeration
          +--ro operational-data
          |  +--ro topic-name?     inet:host-name
          |  +--ro subject-name?   inet:host-name
          +--ro symptom!
             +--ro id               yang:uuid
             +--ro concern-score    score
  ]]></sourcecode>
        </section>
        <section title="YANG Module">
        <sourcecode name="ietf-relevant-state@2025-11-15.yang" type="yang" markers="true"><![CDATA[
module ietf-relevant-state {
  yang-version 1.1;
  namespace "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-relevant-state";
  prefix rsn;

  import ietf-yang-types {
    prefix yang;
    reference
      "draft-ietf-netmod-rfc6991-bis-18: Common YANG Data Types";
  }
  import ietf-inet-types {
    prefix inet;
    reference
      "draft-ietf-netmod-rfc6991-bis-18: Common YANG Data Types";
  }

  organization
    "IETF NMOP Working Group";
  contact
    "WG Web:   <https://datatracker.ietf.org/wg/nmop/>
     WG List:  <mailto:nmop@ietf.org>

     Editor:   Vincenzo Riccobene
              <mailto:vincenzo.riccobene@huawei-partners.com>
              Thomas Graf
              <mailto:thomas.graf@swisscom.com>
              Wanting Du
              <mailto:wanting.du@swisscom.com>
              Alex Huang Feng
              <mailto:alex.huang-feng@insa-lyon.fr>";
  description
    "This module defines the relevant-state container and
     notifications to be used by a network anomaly detection
     system. The defined objects can be used to augment
     operational network collected observability data and
     analytical problem data equally. Describing the relevant-state
     of observed symptoms.

     Copyright (c) 2025 IETF Trust and the persons
     identified as authors of the code.  All rights reserved.

     Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or
     without modification, is permitted pursuant to, and subject
     to the license terms contained in, the Revised BSD License
     set forth in Section 4.c of the IETF Trust's Legal Provisions
     Relating to IETF Documents
     (https://trustee.ietf.org/license-info).

     All revisions of IETF and IANA published modules can be found
     at the YANG Parameters registry
     (https://www.iana.org/assignments/yang-parameters).

     This version of this YANG module is part of RFC XXXX; see
     the RFC itself for full legal notices.";

  revision 2025-11-15 {
    description
      "Initial version";
    reference
      "RFC XXX: Semantic Metadata Annotation for Network Anomaly
       Detection";
  }

  typedef score {
    type uint8 {
      range "0..100";
    }
    description
      "Number that indicates a score between 0 and 100.";
  }

  identity network-anomaly-stage {
    description
      "Base identity for representing the of the network anomaly
       stage.";
    reference
      "Section 6 in draft-ietf-nmop-network-anomaly-lifecycle.";
  }

  identity detection {
    base network-anomaly-stage;
    description
      "A problem is int the detection stage.";
    reference
      "Section 6.1 in draft-ietf-nmop-network-anomaly-lifecycle.";
  }

  identity validation {
    base network-anomaly-stage;
    description
      "A problem is int the validation stage.";
    reference
      "Section 6.2 in draft-ietf-nmop-network-anomaly-lifecycle.";
  }

  identity refinement {
    base network-anomaly-stage;
    description
      "A problem is int the refinement stage.";
    reference
      "Section 6.3 in draft-ietf-nmop-network-anomaly-lifecycle.";
  }

  identity problem-forecasted {
    base detection;
    description
      "A problem has been forecasted, as it is expected that
       the indicated list of symptoms will impact a service
       in the near future.";
  }

  identity problem-potential {
    base detection;
    description
      "A problem has been detected with a confidence
       lower than 100%. In order to confirm that this set of
       symptoms are generating service impact, it requires further
       validation.";
  }

  identity problem-confirmed {
    base validation;
    description
      "After validation, the problem has been confirmed.";
  }

  identity discarded {
    base validation;
    description
      "After validation, the network anomaly has been
       discarded, as there is no evindence that it is causing a
       problem.";
  }

  identity analyzed {
    base refinement;
    description
      "The anomaly detection went through analysis to identify
       potential ways to further improve the detection process in
       for future anomalies.";
  }

  identity adjusted {
    base refinement;
    description
      "The network anomaly has been solved and analysed.
       No further action is required.";
  }

  identity pattern {
    description
      "Pattern identified by the Detector.";
  }

  identity drop {
    base pattern;
    description
      "Drop of the value.";
  }

  identity spike {
    base pattern;
    description
      "Spike of the value.";
  }

  identity mean-shift {
    base pattern;
    description
      "Shift of the mean of the value.";
  }

  identity seasonality-shift {
    base pattern;
    description
      "Shift of the seasonality of the value.";
  }

  identity trend {
    base pattern;
    description
      "Trend exhibited by the value.";
  }

  identity other {
    base pattern;
    description
      "Any other type of pattern.";
  }

  grouping relevant-state-grouping {
    description
      "Relevant State is a state that could lead to
       problems or might be clear indications of problem
       already happening.";
    reference
      "Figure 4 in draft-ietf-nmop-terminology.";
    leaf id {
      type yang:uuid;
      mandatory true;
      description
        "Unique ID of the relevant state. It is unique
         in the scope of the Label Store.";
    }
    leaf uri {
      type inet:uri;
      description
        "URI to viusalize the analytical metrics of the
         relevant-state.";
    }
    leaf description {
      type string;
      description
        "Textual description of the fault.";
    }
    leaf start-time {
      type yang:date-and-time;
      mandatory true;
      description
        "Date and time indicating the beginning of the problem.";
    }
    leaf end-time {
      type yang:date-and-time;
      description
        "Date and time indicating the end of the problem.";
    }
    leaf strategy {
      type string;
      mandatory false;
      description
        "Captures one approach to look at the data (as a human operator
         does) to observe if an abnormal situation is arising.";
      reference
        "Section 3.5.3 in
         draft-ietf-nmop-network-anomaly-architecture.";
    }
    leaf confidence-score {
      type score;
      description
        "Indicates how confident the detector detected an outlier. The
         higher the value the higher the confidence in relation to the
         overall relevant state.";
    }
    leaf concern-score {
      type score;
      mandatory true;
      description
        "Indicates how concerned network operation on connectivity
         service degradation should be. The higher the value the higher
         the concern in relation to the overall relevant state.";
    }
    leaf stage {
      type identityref {
        base network-anomaly-stage;
      }
      mandatory true;
      description
        "Stage of the relevant state.";
    }
    choice service {
      description
        "Indication of the service that is affected
         (or potentially affected) by the relevant state";
    }
  }

  grouping annotator-grouping {
    description
      "Annotator represents the entity that produced the
       annotation (it is either a human or an algorithm).";
    leaf id {
      type yang:uuid;
      description
        "Unique ID of the annotator (either user or algorithm).";
    }
    leaf name {
      type string;
      mandatory true;
      description
        "Name of the annotator (either user or algorithm).";
    }
    leaf version {
      type string;
      mandatory false;
      description
        "Version of the annotator.";
    }
    leaf annotator-type {
      type enumeration {
        enum human {
          description
            "This option is used if a human provided the label.";
        }
        enum algorithm {
          description
            "This option is used if a algorithm or software
             provided the label.";
        }
      }
      description
        "An annotator can be either a human user or a
         programmatic entity, such as an algorithm.";
    }
  }

  grouping message-broker-grouping {
    description
      "References message broker draft-ietf-nmop-yang-message-broker-integration entities.";
    leaf topic-name {
      type inet:host-name;
      description
        "From which message broker topic the operational data was consumed from.";
    }
    leaf subject-name {
      type inet:host-name;
      description
        "To which message broker subject the operational data references to.";
    }
  }

  grouping anomaly-grouping {
    description
      "List of anomalies that are part of the relevant state";
    list anomaly {
      key "id revision";
      description
        "List of Anomaly instances.";
      leaf id {
        type yang:uuid;
        description
          "Unique identifier of the anomaly.";
      }
      leaf revision {
        type yang:counter32;
        description
          "Revision of the anomaly metadata object.
            It allows multiple revisions of the metadata to be
            generated in order to support the definition of
            multiple problem objects from the same source to
            facilitate improvements overtime.";
      }
      leaf uri {
        type inet:uri;
        description
          "URI to viusalize the analytical metrics of the
           anomaly.";
      }
      leaf stage {
        type identityref {
          base network-anomaly-stage;
        }
        mandatory true;
        description
          "Stage of the anomaly.";
      }
      leaf description {
        type string;
        description
          "Textual description of the anomaly.";
      }
      leaf start-time {
        type yang:date-and-time;
        mandatory true;
        description
          "Date and time indicating the beginning of the anomaly.
            A detection system will alwasys set a start time,
            as it represents the moment in time from which the
            behaviour of the monitored system is considered
            to be anomalous with respect its expected behaviour.";
      }
      leaf end-time {
        type yang:date-and-time;
        description
          "Date and time indicating the end of the anomaly.
            This field is indicated as non mandatory, as it could
            be the case that the anomaly is still happening at the
            time of generation of the label.";
      }
      leaf confidence-score {
        type score;
        description
          "Indicates how confident the detector detected an outlier. The
           higher the value the higher the confidence in relation to the
           anomaly.";
      }
      leaf pattern {
        type identityref {
          base pattern;
        }
        description
          "Pattern describes the type of pattern that was
            detected by the annotator (e.g. spike, drop,
            mean-shift, etc.).";
      }
      container annotator {
        description
          "Annotator represents the entity that produced the
            annotation.";
        uses annotator-grouping;
      }
      container operational-data {
        description
          "References the operational data from where the anomaly was observed.";
        uses message-broker-grouping;
      }
      container symptom {
        presence "It specifies the symptom for the anomaly";
        description
          "An observable Characteristic, State, Event, or
           Condition considered as an indication of a Problem
           or potential Problem.";
        leaf id {
          type yang:uuid;
          mandatory true;
          description
            "Unique identifier of the symptom type.";
        }
        leaf concern-score {
          type score;
          mandatory true;
          description
            "Score indicating the degree of concern in
              relation to the specific symptom. Each
              symptom will carry a certain degree of
              concern that is specific to the symptom.";
        }
      }
    }
  }

  notification relevant-state-notification {
    description
      "Notification of a relevant state that can be sent by the
       anomaly detection system to the postmortem management
       system or to the incident management system.";
    container publisher {
      description
        "Publisher represents the entity that produced the
          relevant-state.";
      leaf id {
        type yang:uuid;
        description
          "Unique ID of the publisher.";
      }
      leaf name {
        type string;
        mandatory true;
        description
          "Name of the publisher.";
      }
      leaf version {
        type string;
        mandatory false;
        description
          "Version of the publisher.";
      }
    }
    uses relevant-state-grouping;
    uses anomaly-grouping;
  }

  container relevant-state {
    description
      "A Relevant State is a state that have relevancy
       for network operators, as those are states that could lead
       to problems or might be clear indications of problem already
       happening.";
    uses relevant-state-grouping;
    uses anomaly-grouping;
  }
}
]]></sourcecode>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Implementation" title="Implementation status">
      <t>This section provides pointers to existing open source
      implementations of this document. Note to the RFC-editor: Please
      remove this before publishing. </t>

      <section anchor="Implementation-Antagonist" title="Antagonist">
        <t>An open-source implementation for this document is called
        AnTagOnIst (Anomaly Tagging On hIstorical data), and it has been
        implemented in order to validate the application of the YANG
        model defined in this document. Antagonist provides visual
        support for two important use cases in the scope of this
        document: <ul>
            <li>the generation of a ground truth in relation to symptoms
            and Problems in timeseries data</li>

            <li>the visual validation of results produced by automated
            network anomaly detection tools.</li>
          </ul> The open-source code can be found here: <xref
        target="Antagonist"/></t>

        <t>
        As part of the experiment that was conducted with AnTagOnIst, 
        Some main Use Case scenarios have been validated so far:
        
        <list>
          <t>Exposure of a GUI for human validation of the labels.</t>
          
          <t>Integration with Rule Based anomaly detection systems. 
          In particular the integration with SAIN and Cosmos Bright
          Lights is ongoing.</t>
          
          <t>Integration with ML-based detection systems.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">

      <t>This section is modeled after the template described in
      <xref section="3.7" sectionFormat="of"
      target="I-D.ietf-netmod-rfc8407bis"/>.</t>

      <t>The "ietf-network-anomaly-symptom-cbl" and 
      "ietf-network-anomaly-service-topology" YANG modules defines two
      data models that are designed to be accessed via YANG-based
      management protocols, such as NETCONF <xref target="RFC6141"/> and
      RESTCONF <xref target="RFC8040"/>. These protocols have to use a
      secure transport layer (e.g., SSH <xref target="RFC4252"/>, TLS
      <xref target="RFC8446"/>, and QUIC <xref target="RFC9000"/>) and
      have to use mutual authentication.</t>

      <t>The Network Configuration Access Control Model (NACM) <xref
      target="RFC8341"/> provides the means to restrict access for
      particular NETCONF or RESTCONF users to a preconfigured subset of
      all available NETCONF or RESTCONF protocol operations and content.
      </t>

      <t>There are a number of data nodes defined in this YANG module
      that are writable/creatable/deletable (i.e., "config true", which
      is the default).  All writable data nodes are likely to be
      reasonably sensitive or vulnerable in some network environments. 
      Write operations (e.g., edit-config) and delete operations to
      these data nodes without proper protection or authentication can
      have a negative effect on network operations.  The following
      subtrees and data nodes have particular
      sensitivities/vulnerabilities:</t>

      <t>"There are no particularly sensitive writable data nodes."</t>

      <t>Some of the readable data nodes in this YANG module may be
      considered sensitive or vulnerable in some network environments.
      It is thus important to control read access (e.g., via get,
      get-config, or notification) to these data nodes. Specifically,
      the following subtrees and data nodes have particular
      sensitivities/ vulnerabilities:</t>

      <t>"There are no particularly sensitive readable data nodes."</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors would like to thank Antonio Roberto for his
      contribution to the ideas in this document and Mohamed Boucadair
      and Adrian Farrel, Paul Aitken, Reshad Rahman and Ruediger Geib
			for his review and valuable comments. </t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="https://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>

      <?rfc include='https://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4252.xml'?>
  
      <?rfc include='https://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6141.xml'?>

      <?rfc include='https://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8040.xml'?>

      <?rfc include="https://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="https://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8340.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="https://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8341.xml"?>

      <?rfc include='https://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8446.xml'?>

      <?rfc include='https://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9000.xml'?>

      <?rfc include="https://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9417.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="https://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9418.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="https://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9232.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="https://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9543.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml-ids/reference.I-D.ietf-nmop-network-anomaly-semantics.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml-ids/reference.I-D.ietf-nmop-terminology.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml-ids/reference.I-D.ietf-nmop-network-anomaly-architecture.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml-ids/reference.I-D.ietf-netmod-rfc6991-bis.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml-ids/reference.I-D.ietf-nmop-yang-message-broker-integration.xml"?>

      <reference anchor="Antagonist"
                 target="https://github.com/vriccobene/antagonist">
        <front>
          <title>Antagonist: Anomaly tagging on historical data</title>

          <author fullname="Vincenzo Riccobene" initials="V."
                  surname="Riccobene"/>

          <author fullname="Wanting Du" initials="W." surname="Du"/>

          <author fullname="Thomas Graf" initials="T." surname="Graf"/>

          <author fullname="Alex Huang Feng" initials="H."
                  surname="Huang Feng"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='https://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml-ids/reference.I-D.ietf-netmod-rfc8407bis.xml'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
